Floyd S. Fierman papers, ca. 1850-1997 (bulk: 1870 - 1970)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Floyd S. Fierman papers, ca. 1850-1997 (bulk: 1870-1970)
SJA 003
Fierman, Floyd S.
The material in this collection is organized into two groupings, according to the geographic location of the Jewish individuals, families, or institutions researched. The first four boxes contain materials relevant to New Mexico's Jewish history. The last three boxes contain materials relevant to the Jewish history of western Texas.
8.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
This collection was compiled between 1949-1989 by Rabbi Floyd Fierman, Ph.D. (1917-1989), who served Temple Mount Sinai of El Paso, Texas from 1949 to 1979. His leadership in the community extended far beyond the temple. He was actively engaged in combating racism and fighting for civil rights in El Paso. He was also dedicated to interfaith education and communication and to tracking the history of Jews in the binational southwest.
This collection is the result of his interest in the careers and accomplishments of Jewish pioneers who moved west with their families seeking opportunities of various sorts. As these pioneers settled, they built synagogues, business interests, and communities. By 1860 there was a strong Jewish presence in America's western-most reaches.
Although Fierman was not trained as a professional historian, his contributions to the field included several books and monographs on Jews of the southwest, including Guts and Ruts: The Jewish Pioneer on the Trail in the American Southwest (1984), and its sequel Roots and Boots (1988). He also wrote for several scholarly journals including Western States Jewish History, American Jewish Historical Quarterly, American Jewish Archives, and Arizona and the Southwest.
In his search for historically-significant materials, Fierman photocopied documents from many regional repositories, such as the New Mexico State Records Center and Archives. He also maintained close contact with archivists and librarians from all over the country in his quest for materials and documents. He developed a particularly close relationship with the late Rabbi Jacob Marcus, archivist and historian at the American Jewish Archives.
A sizable portion of the material collected is a product of Rabbi Fierman's notes as taken down on whatever material was available to him at the moment, including hotel and airplane stationery. He often recopied these notes several times and compiled elaborate appendixes to the files which are often longer and more complex than the original record.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
I. New Mexico's Jewish History
II. Western Texas Jewish History
Scope and Content Note
The material in this collection is organized into two groupings, according to the geographic location of the Jewish individuals, families, or institutions researched. The first four boxes contain materials relevant to New Mexico's Jewish history. The last three boxes contain materials relevant to the Jewish history of western Texas. Folder headings within each grouping are organized alphabetically according to the name of the relevant individual, institution, or the subject matter of the file.
Fierman, Floyd S.; Jews -- New Mexico -- History; Jews -- Texas -- History; Frontier and pioneer life -- New Mexico; Frontier and pioneer life -- Texas; Synagogues -- New Mexico; Synagogues -- Texas; Rabbis -- New Mexico; Rabbis -- Texas; Commerce -- New Mexico -- History; Commerce -- Texas -- History; Jewish merchants -- New Mexico; Jewish merchants -- Texas; Sephardim -- New Mexico; New Mexico -- History -- 19th century; Texas -- History -- 19th century; Manuscript text; Biography
Container List
- Series I: New Mexico’s Jewish History
  - Albert, Harold. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albuquerque, NM: "Carving Out an Identity in the Land of 'Anglos'." Reference to the New Mexico Jewish Historical Society which holds collection of 19th century sheet music from New Mexico's first synagogue. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Altshool, Janet: "The State Dissects Fascism: Multi-Media Event Features Seven Weeks of Visual Arts, Film, and Video." (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alvarez, Don Manuel. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Brief biography of Don Manuel Alvarez (a merchant in New Mexico in the 19th century).
    Professional correspondence from Mr. David Maldie to Manuel Alvarez, April 20, 1841. Letter copied by F. Fierman.
    Manuscript from Vicente Martinez written in Spanish (1833).
    Business inventory written in Spanish by Josias Gregg (1835).
    Professional correspondence from Thompson to Manuel Alvarez and J. Sutton to ensure evidence that Thompson had paid them (October 13, 1837).
    Receipt of payment for gold bullion from Manuel Alvarez (1838).
    Receipt for payment of three hundred dollars to Mr. John Johnson in which Manuel Alvarez was a witness (September 1, 1843).
    Correspondence written in Spanish (February 22,1860).
    Several receipts written in Spanish (1836).
    Inventory written in Spanish (1839,1842,1843).
    Excerpts of the Manuel Alvarez Papers inventory with references to Albert Speyer (1845-1848).
    Statement submitted from merchants of Santa Fe, New Mexico in regard to exported goods to the House of Representatives of the United States. It is signed by Manuel Alvarez for and on behalf of the American merchants in Sante Fe (February 1842).
    Receipt and statement of inventory (Sept. 1, 1842).
  - Amberg family. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence between Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives and the Amberg family (1992-1995).
    Part of the genealogy of the Amberg family (1993,1994).
    Genealogy of the Amberg family (1770-1976).
  - Amberg, Jacob: "The Promised Land," Albuquerque Journal, Section D; p. 1,3 (April 22, 1990); Jacob Amberg is mentioned. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anti-Defamation League. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Article provides discussion of Jewish/Christian dialogue in Santa Fe.
    Three articles relating to the Greater Albuquerque and the New Mexico Anti-Defamation League.
  - Anti-Semitism in New Mexico. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Appel, Alvin. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Personal correspondence regarding the genealogy of the Appel family (1992).
    Segment of "Memoirs of Alvin Appel" written by Alvin Appel. Appel discusses his early years in Las Vegas, New Mexico.
    Chronological, geographical, and statistical information organized by Alvin Appel. Maps indicating residential and commercial areas in Las Vegas, New Mexico in the nineteenth century. An analysis of vital records of Montefiore cemetery (founded 1881). Chronological order of burial dates, births, and longevity record, and a summary of mortality records.
    Appel genealogy beginning with Abraham Appel (March 24, 1840).
  - Baer, Louis. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Banking (New Mexico). (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Professional correspondence regarding Jewish banking in New Mexico (1965).
    List of charter members of the Bank of New Mexico (1853).
    From Parish, William - "Merchant Banking in Early New Mexico," Mid-Continent Banker vol. 51, no. 7 (July 1955). Refers to merchant banking in New Mexico, Rabbi Moise Bergman, and Solomon Beuthner.
  - Bauman. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bellman, Samuel. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Correspondence between Abraham Chanin and Ethel Schwartz regarding Samuel Bellman.
    Four indentures, five warrantee deeds, two quitclaim deeds, four mortgage deeds, and two chattel mortgages - all in the name of Samuel Bellman.
    Professional correspondence from attorney to Samuel Bellman regarding a defective title (1914).
    Regards exact location of property purchased (1916).
  - Bergman, Rabbi Moise. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bernalillo Mercantile. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Newspapers article from Klemz, Victoria -"Bernalillo Mercantile Changes Hands from Seligman to Craft," Sandoval County Review (August 7, 1978).
    Historical discussion of the Old Bernalillo Mercantile, from Klemz, Victoria -"The 'Merc' in Bernalillo Part of Historical Sandoval County," Sandoval County Review (June 1978).
    Professional correspondence from Jack Seligman (1947, 1978).
    Professional correspondence to Siegfried Seligman (June 22, 1945).
    Article from Brown Kenneth - "Bernalillo-A City of Action! Ayer, Hoy Y Manana," Northside Story; vol. 1, no. 5 (May 30, 1969); discusses the history of Bernalillo.
    Article from Arango, Polly -"Bernalillo Mercantile Echoes Eras Past," Rio Rancho Roadrunner (January 15,1980); discusses the Bernalillo Mercantile Company's history.
    Advertisement for Bernalillo Mercantile Co.
    Audit report for Bernalillo Mercantile Company (February 28, 1941).
    Contract between Bernalillo Mercantile and Cubero Trading Company for merchandise sold at twenty thousand dollars (July 1915).
    Census of Las Cruces (1900).
    Check issued to Mr. Seligman from First National Bank (June 23, 1886).
    Bernalillo Mercantile Company combined balance sheet (February 28, 1941).
    Receipt from Bernalillo Mercantile Company.
    References to court filings.
    Organizational minutes of the Bernalillo Mercantile Company and minutes of the Board of Directors (1903,1913,1914).
    Outline for the yearly report (1940-1941) of the Bernalillo Mercantile Company.
  - Bernstein, Morris J.: Article mentions Morris Bernstein (lacks any citations). (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Beuthner, Solomon. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bibo, Arthur. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Manuscript of telephone conversation between F. Fierman and Irman Bibo (Jan. 19, 1979).
    Correspondence between F. Fierman and Arthur Bibo regarding primary documents of the Bibo family (March 19, 1954).
    Correspondence from Arthur Bibo's wife (first name not available) to F. Fierman regarding the condition of her husband (September 8, 1967).
    Correspondences from Arthur Bibo to F. Fierman regarding Bibo genealogy (1964) and family photographs (1961).
    Correspondence between Arthur Bibo and F. Fierman (1954-1960).
    Introduction to biography on Arthur Bibo written by F. Fierman. Includes endnotes.
  - Bibo, Charles. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bibo family. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Genealogy of the Bibo family (1807-1965).
    F. Fierman's correspondences concerning the Bibo family history.
    Correspondence from Simon Bibo to Albuquerque Lodge (March 15, 1883).
    Correspondence in which Simon Bibo requests aid in finding a school for his children and housing in Los Angeles.
    Marriage announcement of Solomon Bibo's daughter, Clara (July 31, 1909).
    Ripp, Bart - "World Has Retreated From Bibo: Lifelong Resident Enjoys Quiet and Colorful Memories," The Albuquerque Tribune.
    Gugliotta, Bobette - Katzimo, Mysterious Mesa (Dodd, Mead, and Company: New York).
    Carson, Kit, "That 100,000 Loot In the Malpais Country!" True West.
    Newspaper article - discusses a sixth generation Bibo in Sante Fe, Jim Bibo.
    Stern, Norton B. "Jewish Indian Chief Simon Bibo."
    Court cases relating to the Bibo Family (1884-1913).
    Article - "The Promised Land," Albuquerque Journal (April 22, 1990).
  - Bibo, Nathan (1 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Manuscript notes regarding Nathan Bibo; written by F. Fierman.
    Nathan Bibo presents the history of the Bibo family in a series of five articles - "Reminiscences of Early New Mexico," Albuquerque Sunday Herald (June 4, June 11, June 18, July 2, and July 9, 1922).
    Copy of professional correspondence to the Bureau of Indian Affairs from the Citizens of the Pueblo de Acoma asking the government not to revoke the trading license of Solomon Bibo, their trader (July 21, 1884).
    Copy of United States Bill from the United States senate authorizing that the treasury pay Nathan Bibo, Sr. a said amount for the compensation of loss of property.
    "Central Bank Signature Book Dated August 18, 1882, Will be Displayed Here," Albuquerque Journal (June 10,1956); discussion of Old Central Bank signature book found with signatures from Emil, Simon, and Solomon Bibo.
    Copy of list of commissioned officers and date of appointment, resignation, and discharge.
    Newspaper article on Nathan Bibo - "Pioneer, Oldest Resident in Bernalillo." Article lacks full citation. Discusses Bibo's philosophy toward American Indians (Navajo and Apache).
    An untitled biography of the Bibo family, specifically Nathan and Solomon Bibo, written by F. Fierman.
    Manuscript written by Nathan Bibo regarding his trip from Bernallillo to Camp Whipple in 1873.
    Correspondence from Irving Bibo to F. Fierman regarding family genealogy (1953,1961).
    Correspondence from archivist at State of New Mexico Office of State Records Center regarding the Bibo family.
    Professional correspondence from Nathan Bibo to the Governor of New Mexico regarding American Indian policy.
    Correspondence from the Indian Rights Association to Nathan Bibo responding favorably toward Bibo's American Indian policy.
    Correspondence from Nathan Bibo to the President of the State Federation of Women Clubs (Grace Thorpe Baer) regarding American Indian education (June 7, 1925).
    Copy of correspondence from Nathan Bibo to David Starr Jordan at Stanford University in regard to American Indians (1925).
    Copy of correspondence from Nathan Bibo to Clara True in regard to American Indians (May 25, 1925).
    Correspondence from Irving Bibo to F. Fierman regarding Nathan Bibo.
    Bibo, Nathan -"Pioneer Settler Says Old Clique Governs Indians: Ancient Customs and Pagan Traditions Prevail in Pueblos Bernalillo Man Declares," Albuquerque Morning Journal.
  - Bibo, Nathan (2 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Governors Papers, James F.Hinkle, State Records Center and Archives (November 5, 1923).
    Copy of article in which Nathan Bibo addresses the state of the American Indian in New Mexico.
    Bibo, Nathan - "Nathan Bibo Answers Article on Pueblo Indian Questions: Gives Facts Vs. Fiction," Albuquerque Herald, Albuquerque, New Mexico (August 19, 1923). Nathan Bibo addresses the Association of Women of New Mexico regarding the state of the Pueblo Indian in New Mexico.
    Handwritten note written by Nathan Bibo (date unknown).
    White, Leslie A. - "The Acoma Indians: Forty-Seventh Annual Report of the Bureau of Ethnology (1929-30); Washington, D.C.: United States Printing Office (pp. 23-125).
    "Nathan Bibo and The Railroad" was written on the back of an old stove brochure (1922).
    Article - "Setting Bibo Right" (attacks Nathan Bibo's article on the Pueblo Indian question).
    Genealogy of the Bibo family compiled by F. Fierman.
    Description of photos of Bibo family (taken in New Mexico).
    Copy of "A Nathan Bibo Memoir From His 'I Am It' Notebook: Trip to Bland Mountain" (1920).
  - Bibo, Solomon. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Correspondence from O. W. Holmes (Chief Archivist at the National Archives and Records Service) to F. Fierman regarding records from the Bureau of Indian Affairs (1954).
    Notes by Mrs. Erich Spier regarding a steamship ticket, birth certificate and certificate of dismissal from the German Army all in the name of Solomon Bibo.
    Correspondence between the United States Indian Service and the Pueblo Indian Agency regarding Solomon Bibo and trade (August 24, 1844).
    Copy of application from Solomon Bibo for license of trade with the Pueblo Indians (December 12, 1882). There is also a bond enclosed.
    Copy of correspondence from Pedro Sanchez (U.S. Indian Agent at the Pueblo Agency) to Commissioner of Indian Affairs, stating that Solomon Bibo desired to move his goods from Acoma to Grant's station (July 18, 1883).
    Copy of correspondence from Martin Valle transmitting a petition signed by him and nearly every citizen of his Pueblo requesting that the trader's license issued to Solomon Bibo not be revoked. Petition enclosed (July 22, 1984).
    Copy of application of Solomon Bibo for license to trade at the Acoma Pueblo (December 22, 1882).
    Copy of list of documents relating to the Bibos of New Mexico (1882-1886).
    Copy of certification of U.S. citizenship for Solomon Bibo (date unavailable).
    Copy of miscellaneous legal documents concerning Solomon Bibo (in Spanish; 1888).
    Bronitsky, Gordon, "Indians and Jews at Acoma: Reading Draft."
    Correspondence between Arthur Bibo and the American Jewish Archives and Universal Jewish Encyclopedia.
    New Mexico citation from the Universal Jewish Encyclopedia (1948).
    Bronitsky, Gordon - "Solomon Bibo: Jew and Indian at Acoma Pueblo."
    Rollins, Sandra Lea - "Jewish Indian Chief," Western States Jewish Historical Quarterly.
    Martinez, Demetria - "Jewish Immigrant Was Acoma Governor: Lecture Sunday Tells How Solomon Bibo Was Elected Indian Official."
    "Third Generation Bibo Opening New Store: New Chapter Begins in Saga of Bibos," (September 8, 1967).
  - Biernbaum, Henry. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Blackmore, William: Manuscript notes from Brayer, H.O. - "William Blackmore: The Spanish Mexican Land Grants of New Mexico and Colorado 1863-1878" (1949). (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bloom, Rabbi Herbert. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Correspondence from Leopold Meyer to William Parish (January 11, 1960).
    Copy of correspondence from Herbert Boom to Leopold (January 4, 1960).
  - Blun Brothers. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Correspondence to F. Fierman from Jerome Schloss (January 16, 1969).
    Fierman's scribbled notes regarding the Blun brothers (1982).
  - B'nai B'rith. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Copy of B'nai B'rith Cemetery Association meeting notes (March 3, 1889 to January 12, 1902).
    Correspondence to the officers and members of Albuquerque Lodge (1885).
    Card of withdrawal issued to David Weinman from the Joshua Lodge branch of B'nai B'rith.
    Copy of request to a Lodge in Zanesville, Ohio (December 28, 1884).
    Correspondence and official documents of B'nai B'rith lodges in New Mexico (1883-1898).
  - B'nai Shalom Havurah: "Taos Havurah Hosts Rabbi For Holidays," The Link (September 1996). (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Bromberg, Herman: Obituary for Herman Bromberg (source and date unavailable). (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Bronitsky, Gordon. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Bronitsky, Gordon - "The Crypto-Jewish Question in New Mexico," The Link.
    Bronitsky, Gordon - "Jewish/Indian Dialog in Tucson."
    Bronitsky, Gordon - "Blacks and Jews in New Mexico," The Link.
    Bronitsky, Gordon - "You're From Where? I Didn't Know There Were Any Jews There!," The Link.
    Bronitsky, Gordon - Untitled, The Link.
    Bronitsky, Gordon - "Jewish Geography-- New Mexico Style," The Link.
    Gordon Bronitsky's resume.
    Bronitsky, Gordon - "New Mexico's First Synagogue," The Link.
    Bronitsky, Gordon - "Solomon Bibo: Jew and Indian at Acoma Pueblo," The Link.
    Bronitsky, Gordon - "Like Jews, Indians Strive For Cultural Survival," The New York Jewish...
    Bronitsky, Gordon - "Marranos, Merchants, and Indian Chiefs: Jews of the Southwest."
    A short summary of Gordon Bronitsky's career.
  - Brookins, Douglas G.: Obituary for Douglas G. Brookins entitled "Former Temple Resident Dies" (June 1991). (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Brunswick, Marcus: "A New Mexican In Washington," Eddy County News. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Camden De Leon, David: Copy of legal documents from New Mexico and the United States of America regarding a case involving Camden De Leon (1851-1872). (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Carlsbad, NM: Article - (Sparks, J.W.) "History of the Carlsbad, New Mexico, Jewish Congregation, 1916-1989." (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Cattle brands: Fierman's notes on cattle brands in New Mexico. Also, Appendix from "Cattle and Miners." (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Celnik, Rabbi Isaac. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Biography of Rabbi Isaac Celnik.
    "B'nai Israel to Honor Celnik for 25 Years at Congregation" (December 1997).
  - Chapman, Rabbi Ed E.: Article - (Goldstein, Rabbi Raphael) "American Judaism in the Making" (June 22, 1923). (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Citrin, Paul J.: Article - "State of Israel Bonds Honors Citrin" (November 1991). (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Clever, Charles P. (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Copy of document signed by the President of the United States appointing Clever Marshal of the United States for the territory of New Mexico.
    Article - (Fierman, F.) "The Frontier Career of Charles Clever," El Palacio.
    Note cards which lead to references to Charles Clever.
    F. Fierman's manuscript notes pertaining to a manuscript on Charles Clever.
    F. Fierman's scribbled notes regarding the history of Charles Clever.
    Copies of correspondence between General Clever and his subordinates (1863-1865). Correspondence between F. Fierman and various archives and libraries regarding information on C. Clever.
    Article - (Turner, Virginia) "How It Started" (February 25, 1980).
    F. Fierman's rudimentary introduction to a work entitled "C.P. Cleaver."
    Article - (Fierman) "From Guten Tag to Buenos Dios: The New Mexico Territory Through the Eyes and Life of Charles P. Clever."
    Copy of manuscripts from Sante Fe, New Mexico (December 31, 1859).
    F. Fierman's appendix for a manuscript on Charles Clever.
    F. Fierman's manuscript notes relating to Charles Clever.
    Original handwritten manuscript entitled 'C.P. Clever' (by F. Fierman).
    Note cards written by F. Fierman regarding Charles Clever.
  - Clever, Charles P. (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 41)
    A copy of the order warning against fraud in the payment of militia claims on the part of war veterans (in Spanish, with English translation).
    Article - (Clever Charles P.) "New Mexico: Her Resources; Her Necessities For Railroad Communication With the Atlantic and Pacific States; Her Great Future" (Washington D.C.: McGill and Witherow, Printers and Stereotypers, 1868).
    Original manuscript - "The New Mexico Territory: As Seen Through the Life and Eyes of C.P. Clever" (by F. Fierman).
    Several general orders issued by Charles P. Clever from his position as Adjutant General of New Mexico (1861-1862).
    Correspondence between Charles Clever and military officials (1861-66; in English and Spanish).
    Several articles from The New Mexican which refer to Charles Clever (1864-1869).
    Correspondence from the Headquarters Department of New Mexico to Charles Clever (1855).
    Article - "Clever in A New Role" (October 21, 1868).
    Correspondence from Attorney General of New Mexico to Charles Clever (July 9, 1864).
  - Cohen, Abraham: Article - (Zimmerman, Rebecca) "Family Gives $500,000 for JCC" (January 1995). (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Cohen, Harris. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Statement for the plaintiffs in the District Court in the county of Bernalillo, New Mexico (May 1866).
    Court order from the District Court (April 20, 1866).
    Statement which posits that Cohn vs. Jaroslawski Bros. was dismissed by agreement, at the cost of the plaintiffs (May 1866).
    Transcription of court hearing for the case Jaroslawski Bros. vs Harris Cohn (1866).
    Papers relating to the court case Jaroslawski Bros. vs Harris Cohn (1866).
    Copy of original and transcribed copy done by F. Fierman.
  - Cohen, J.N. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Columbus, NM. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Article - (McGaw, W.C.) "A Raid Is A Raid Is A Raid."
    Reprint of March 18, 1916 newspaper (Las Cruces Citizen)
    Article - "Today's Comment: Arthur Ravels Gives Graphic Account of a Night of Terror When Columbus Was Raided By Poncho Villa's Bandits" (Saturday, March 15, 1958).
    Article - (Danoff, H.O.) "Indian Traders of the Southwest: The Danoffs of New Mexico."
  - Conferences: Announcement of New Mexico Jewish Historical Society's Annual Conference. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Congregation Albert (Albuquerque). (Box 1, Folder 47)